A Finding Aid tot he Elizabeth Piutti-Barth Papers, circa 1875-1953, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Elizabeth Piutti-Barth papers
circa 1875-1953
Archives of American Art
Piutti-Barth, Elizabeth, 1872-1959
AAA.piuteliz
Archival Resource Key
0.2 Linear feet
The papers of Boston-based portrait painter Elizabeth Piutti-Barth measure 0.2 linear feet and date from circa 1975 to 1953. Found is a lecture, printed material, and photographs of Piutti-Barth, her family, friends, subjects, homes and studios, and works of art.
Biographical / Historical
Elizabeth Piutti-Barth (1872-1959) was a portrait painter in Boston, Massachusetts.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Boston-based portrait painter Elizabeth Piutti-Barth measure 0.2 linear feet and date from circa 1975 to 1953. Found is a lecture, printed material, and photographs of Piutti-Barth, her family, friends, subjects, homes and studios, and works of art.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Erica Cawley, the daughter of Elizabeth Piutt-Barth, in 1982.
Existence and Location of Copies
The collection is available on 35mm microfilm reel 3813-3814 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Women artists; Women painters; Portrait painters -- Massachusetts -- Boston
- Elizabeth Piutti-Barth Papers, circa 1875-1953; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  An undated typescript of a lecture is entitled "Painting a Portrait." Printed materials include exhibition catalogs and invitations and clippings. The bulk of the papers consists of photographs including snapshots and portraits. Found are photographs of Piutti-Barth as a child and throughout her life, with her artwork, family, friends, and subjects. Also found are photos of her St. Botolph studio, her home, and her still-life and portrait paintings. Subjects of portrait paintings include Governor of Massachusetts Frank Allen, the actress Jeanne Eagles, musicians, and others, many of whom are unidentified.
  - Lecture, circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Printed Material, 1911-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Photographs, of Elizabeth Piutti-Barth and Others, circa 1875-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, of Studio and Homes - St. Botolph Studio, Boston, 1909-1926; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, of Studio and Homes - Studio Home, Cambridge, Massachusetts, undated and 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, Portrait of Daughter (Erica Cowley), 1910-1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, Portraits of Children, 1911-1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, Portraits of Men, 1911-1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, Portraits of Women, 1909-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)